{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "The 1st Texas Infantry lost over 80 percent of its men at this battle, the highest regimental casualty rate on either side of the entire war. George Anderson was one of six generals killed at this battle, having suffered a wound while defending the Bloody Lane. This battle, commonly known as Sharpsburg in the South, took place on September 17th, 1862 and resulted in over 22,000 casualties. For ten points, name this battle in Maryland, the bloodiest single-day battle of the Civil War.",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Antietam",
        "Battle of Sharpsburg before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A disaster at this site forced nearby residents to move to the newly constructed city of Slavutych and prompted the construction of an iron sarcophagus to enclose this site. Sweden experienced an incidence of acid rain after a disaster at this site, which is now part of a zone of alienation. The Red Forest was created and Pripyat, Ukraine was rendered uninhabitable by the failure of, for ten points, what Soviet nuclear power plant that melted down in 1986?",
      "answer": "Chernobyl Nuclear Power Plant"
    },
    {
      "question": "The rituals of Annaprashana and Mamabhat involve feeding rice to these people. In Japan, the holiday 7-5-3 involves giving these people haircuts. While teaching, Jesus said to bring these people to him and compared them to the ideal kind of faith. A group led by Thomas Muntzer argued against baptizing these people and was known as the Anabaptists. Naming ceremonies are held in honor of, for ten points, what type of people, one of whom is placed in a manger for Christian nativity scenes?",
      "answer": [
        "children",
        "equivalents",
        "infant",
        "baby"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In ancient Rome, a man known as the venatore would hunt these animals in herds as a spectacle for commoners. The ancient Greek class of hippeis was named for their ownership of these animals, which were drowned in a river as an offering to Poseidon. Caligula supposedly planned to appoint one of these animals, Incitatus, as consul. The equite [EK-wee-tay] class of Romans owned, for ten points, what animals used to pull chariots?",
      "answer": "horses"
    },
    {
      "question": "On February 3, 1977, a meeting of this country’s top military council ended in a shootout where fifty-eight people died. That event kicked off this country’s Red Terror in which up to 500,000 people died and the military council, known as the Derg, emerged supreme. In 1983, a massive famine in this country led to international attention, including the Live Aid concerts. For ten points, name this African country that once controlled Eritrea on the Red Sea and has capital Addis Ababa.",
      "answer": "Ethiopia"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man left law school after promising Saint Anna that he would change careers if he survived a lightning storm. Englishman William Tyndale was inspired by this man’s translation of the Bible into vernacular German. This man’s clashes with the ideology of Johann Tetzel led him to be brought before the Diet of Worms. For ten points, name this priest who protested the sale of indulgences by writing the 95 Theses, beginning the Protestant Reformation.",
      "answer": "Martin Luther"
    },
    {
      "question": "A work by this composer states “we cannot escape history,” a quote from a State of the Union address, and incorporates folk songs like “Camptown Races.” Another work by this composer used kettle and snare drums to depict a gunfight and quotes songs like “The Old Chisholm Trail.” A speech by Vice President Henry A. Wallace inspired a piece by this composer that commemorates ordinary American soldiers in World War II. For ten points, name this composer of the ballets Billy the Kid, Lincoln Portrait, and Fanfare For the Common Man.",
      "answer": "Aaron Copland"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was elected to the House in 1946 by labeling his opponent, Jerry Voorhis, a communist. This man won a Senate seat over “the Pink Lady,” Helen Gahagan Douglas, in 1950, but served less than a full term and resigned after successfully running for Vice President. He survived that campaign by delivering the “Checkers” speech. Dwight Eisenhower ran for President on a ticket with, for ten points, what politician who later won two Presidential elections but resigned after Watergate?",
      "answer": "Richard Nixon"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this state, Benjamin Lincoln surrendered a major city on May 12, 1780 after being besieged by British forces for over a month. Defensive structures made of palmetto wood foiled British naval bombardments at Fort Moultrie in this state. Daniel Morgan’s army routed Banastre Tarleton’s dragoons in this state at the Battle of Cowpens. Nathaniel Greene besieged Camden in, for ten points, what southern US state where the Americans surrendered Charleston?",
      "answer": "South Carolina"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this war, two generals played a board game called petteia while, unknown to them, a battle raged around them. The Phrygian king Teleutas died in single combat during this war while fighting Ajax, son of Telamon. To avoid fighting in this war, a man pretended to be senile and plowed his field with salt, but gave up the ruse by swerving to avoid his baby son, Telemachus. For ten points, name this ancient war, the subject of Homer’s Iliad.",
      "answer": "Trojan War"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The 21st specific charge in Richard Nixon’s articles of impeachment concerned a $200,000 bribe to overturn the Price Commission’s ruling on a price increase on this product. Ketchup and mustard are standard on this product, which outperformed a competitor released in the 1980s by the chain A&W because many Americans misunderstood that “one-third” represented a larger, not smaller, fraction. This product is often known as a “Royal” in countries with the metric system. For ten points, name this larger companion of the Big Mac on the McDonald’s menu.",
        "answer": [
          "Quarter Pounder with",
          "without cheese"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This McDonald’s chairman paid $200,000 to Richard Nixon’s re-election campaign in summer 1972 to get permission to raise the price of the Quarter Pounder. McDonald’s exploded into a franchised behemoth after this man entered into a partnership with the original McDonald brothers.",
        "answer": "Ray Kroc"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This group was attacked by “hellburners” near Flanders prior to the Battle of Gravelines. A queen declared that she possessed “the heart and stomach of a king” while rallying resistance against this group in the Tilbury Speech. Sir Francis Drake bragged that he had “singed the beard” of the king after striking this group at Cadiz. Elizabeth I was to be replaced by a Catholic ruler after an attack by, for ten points, what fleet that failed to subdue England in 1588?",
        "answer": "Spanish Armada"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This king of Spain, a son of Charles V, sent the Armada.",
        "answer": "Philip II"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country’s independence fighters included the La Trinitaria society, led by Juan Pablo Duarte. A leader of this country ordered his secret police, the SIM, to murder three of the Mirabal sisters. Many citizens of a neighboring country were murdered by this country’s troops for their pronunciation of the word “perejil” [per-eh-HEEL] in the 1937 Parsley Massacre. For ten points, name this Caribbean country where a dictator known as “El Jefe” [hay-fay] attacked the people of its neighbor, Haiti.",
        "answer": [
          "Dominican Republic",
          "D.R.",
          "Republica Dominicana"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This dictator, known as “El Jefe,” ruled the Dominican Republic for over three decades. The Mirabal sisters were activists against this ruler, who ordered the Parsley Massacre.",
        "answer": "Rafael Trujillo"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At a battle in this state, forces under Sterling Price used bales of water soaked hemp to absorb Union artillery. In addition to the First Battle of Lexington, this state was home to the Battle of Wilson’s Creek, which gave the Confederacy control of its southwestern corner. Bloody Bill Anderson’s bushwhackers carried out the Centralia Massacre in this state, which was admitted to the Union simultaneously with Maine. For ten points, name this state, the subject of an 1820 “Compromise.”",
        "answer": "Missouri"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Among the men who carried out the Centralia Massacre under Bloody Bill Anderson was this man, whose later crimes included a botched bank robbery in Northfield, Minnesota in 1876 with his brother Frank.",
        "answer": "Jesse James"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This speech warns dictators that “those who foolishly sought power by riding the back of the tiger ended up inside.” Ted Sorensen helped draft this speech, whose speaker notes that America “shall pay any price [...] to assure the survival and success of liberty.” The challenge to “ask not what your country can do for you; ask what you can do for your country” was delivered in, for ten points, what January 1961 address?",
        "answer": "John Fitzgerald Kennedy’s inaugural address"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Kennedy’s inaugural ceremonies were the first in which a poet took part; this New Englander recited “The Gift Outright” from memory after sunlight prevented him from reading his intended text.",
        "answer": "Robert Frost"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A global database of incidents of this phenomenon is maintained by the research group START at the University of Maryland. Samuel Scheffler distinguishes “general” and “state” types of this phenonmenon in a 2006 paper, and Robert Pape analyzes the strategic logic of this phenomenon in his 2005 book Dying to Win. This phenomenon’s name can be traced back to the French Revolution, during the so-called “reign” of Robespierre. For ten points, name this phenomenon, broadly defined as intentional violence to coerce or incite fear, as exemplified by the September 11 attacks.",
        "answer": "terrorism"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Samuel Scheffler’s “Is Terrorism Morally Distinctive?” discusses this thinker, who characterized fear as the “worst incommodity of all” in a passage that ends by describing the life of man as “solitary, poor, nasty, brutish, and short” in the state of nature.",
        "answer": "Thomas Hobbes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1731, Ben Franklin founded a subscription-based one of these institutions in Philadelphia. After one of these institutions was destroyed in the British burning of Washington, D.C. during the War of 1812, Thomas Jefferson sold his personal collection to restock it. Over 2,500 of these facilities were built with Andrew Carnegie’s funds. Carnegie helped popularize the “open-shelf” style of, for ten points, what public facilities that include circulation desks and reading rooms?",
        "answer": "library"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Thomas Jefferson’s collection helped rebuild this research library in Washington, D.C., which claims to be the largest library in the world.",
        "answer": "Library of Congress"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A diplomat from this country became known as “Mr. No” because of his frequent vetoes in the United Nations. Another diplomat from this country promulgated the “Sinatra Doctrine” that encouraged countries to settle their own internal affairs. This country invaded Afghanistan in accordance with its Brezhnev Doctrine. Eduard Shevardnadze represented Georgia within, for ten points, what country that led the Warsaw Pact in opposition to NATO during the Cold War?",
        "answer": [
          "Soviet Union",
          "USSR",
          "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics",
          "CCCP",
          "Soyuz Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Brezhnev Doctrine was first described in an article in this Soviet newspaper, whose name means “Truth.”",
        "answer": "Pravda"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The FBI",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "City where FBI headquarters is located on Pennsylvania Avenue, just east of the White House.",
          "answer": [
            "Washington, DC",
            "District of Columbia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Cabinet-level department that oversees the FBI.",
          "answer": "Department of Justice"
        },
        {
          "question": "FBI director from 1924 to 1972 and namesake of their headquarters.",
          "answer": "John Edgar Hoover"
        },
        {
          "question": "Illegal good smuggled by “bootleggers,” early targets of the FBI.",
          "answer": [
            "alcohol",
            "equivalent answers",
            "any specific type"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "FBI director from 2001 to 2013 who served as Special Counsel investigating Russian interference in the 2016 election.",
          "answer": "Robert Mueller"
        },
        {
          "question": "Questionably legal program that infiltrated domestic political groups from 1956 to 1971 and tapped Martin Luther King’s phones.",
          "answer": [
            "COINTELPRO",
            "Counter Intelligence Program"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "FBI Associate Director who acted as “Deep Throat,” a source in the Watergate scandal.",
          "answer": "W. Mark Felt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Executive secretary who assisted in the destruction of thousands of “personal” files after the 1972 death of the FBI director.",
          "answer": "Helen Gandy"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Concert of Europe",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "“Iron Chancellor” of Prussia who recreated the system.",
          "answer": [
            "Otto von Bismarck",
            "Otto Eduard Leopold"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "German city where that chancellor held an 1878 congress to address the Balkans.",
          "answer": "Berlin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Austrian city that names the original version of the Concert, created following the Napoleonic wars.",
          "answer": "Vienna"
        },
        {
          "question": "Year, called the Spring of Nations, in which dozens of revolutions led to the collapse of the first Concert of Europe.",
          "answer": "1848"
        },
        {
          "question": "Austrian diplomat who organized the Concert of Europe in 1815.",
          "answer": "Klemens von Metternich"
        },
        {
          "question": "City that hosted an 1818 congress, eighty years after hosting the peace talks that ended the War of Austrian Succession.",
          "answer": [
            "Aix-la-Chapelle",
            "Aachen"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Alliance organized by Alexander I that united the monarchist powers of Russia, Prussia, and Austria.",
          "answer": [
            "Holy Alliance",
            "Grand Alliance"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "British diplomat who brokered the 1814 Treaty of Chaumont, then pursued non-intervention on the continent.",
          "answer": [
            "Robert Stewart, Viscount Castlereagh",
            "Lord Castlereagh"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "World Holidays",
      "prompt": "Name the holiday on which...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "A World War I truce was called in late December 1914.",
          "answer": "Christmas"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Battle of Puebla is celebrated, more prominently in America than in Mexico.",
          "answer": "Cinco de Mayo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Jews fast and seek atonement, and on which an Arab coalition attacked Israeli forces in 1973.",
          "answer": "Yom Kippur War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Muslims fast and pray; the aforementioned 1973 war took place during this holy month.",
          "answer": "Ramadan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Oceanic troops who fought, particularly at Gallipoli, are remembered on April 25.",
          "answer": "Anzac Day"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Viet Cong launched a massive surprise attack in 1968.",
          "answer": "Tet Offensive"
        },
        {
          "question": "The emancipation of American slaves, specifically Gordon Granger’s proclamation in Galveston, is celebrated.",
          "answer": "Juneteenth"
        },
        {
          "question": "Julius Caesar refused the crown in 44 BC, a month before he was killed.",
          "answer": "Lupercalia"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country’s namesake river passes through its agriculturally rich Fouta region. The MFDC has advocated for the independence of this country’s Casamance region. A holding center for African slaves waiting to be exported operated on this country’s (20 pts)",
        "Goree Island. Leopold Sedar Senghor Airport is in this country, the home of the Serer and Wolof ethnic groups. The (10 pts)",
        "Gambia is surrounded by, for ten points, what former French colony, an African country with capital at Dakar?"
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of Senegal"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man infamously allied his Catholic country with a Protestant nation by signing the Treaty of Barwalde. On the Day of the Dupes, this man nearly lost power when Marie de (20 pts)",
        "Medici attempted to sway opinion against him. A seawall was constructed to obstruct shipping to La Rochelle, a (10 pts)",
        "Huguenot fortress besieged by this man. This man, who was known as the Red Eminence, served as the adviser of Louis XIII. For ten points, name this French cardinal who was succeeded by Mazarin in 1642."
      ],
      "answer": "Cardinal Richelieu or Armand Jean du Plessis"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Rosalynn Carter persuaded politician Wayne Townsend to approve this legislation in Indiana. The court case Idaho v. Freeman concerned the passage of this legislation, which was opposed by the Eagle Forum founded by (20 pts)",
        "Phyllis Schlafly. This legislation failed to become law since only 35 of 38 states ratified it before its (10 pts)",
        "1979 deadline. The N.O.W. supported this legislation at the urging of its author, Alice Paul. For ten points, name this proposed Constitutional amendment that intended to prohibit sex discrimination."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Equal Rights Amendment",
        "ERA"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Poet Duncan Campbell Scott established a boarding school system in this country in the 1920s. This country’s government used eleven Numbered Treaties to take land and resources from its indigenous people. An 1869 rebellion of the (20 pts)",
        "M´etis [may-TEE] people was led by Louis Riel, who was executed on orders of John A. (10 pts)",
        "Macdonald, this country’s first prime minister. The Cree and Ojibwe are the largest subgroups of the First Nations, one of the indigenous groups of, for ten points, what largest North American country?"
      ],
      "answer": "Canada"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader introduced the Restoration of Sovereignty Day in 2013, marking the 61st anniversary of the Americans leaving his country. People have speculated that this leader’s wife, Akie, pretended to not know English to avoid (20 pts)",
        "speaking to Donald Trump at a G-20 summit. During this leader’s tenure, his government faced both nationalistic (10 pts)",
        "anti-Korean riots and the Fukushima nuclear disaster. For ten points, name this Prime Minister of Japan who has led since 2012."
      ],
      "answer": "Shinzo Abe"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s Prime Minister was assassinated by disguised electricians during Operation Ogre. This leader, who was given command of the Army of Africa by Emilio Mola, rose to prominence during the (20 pts)",
        "Rif War in Morocco. This ruler came to power after forming a coalition of the (10 pts)",
        "Falange and Carlists to defeat the Republican faction, but he restored the monarchy before his death, leading to the ascension of Juan Carlos I. For ten points, name this fascist dictator of Spain."
      ],
      "answer": "Francisco Franco"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An artist from this movement painted Woman and Child on a Balcony, whose central figures look toward the golden dome of the Les Invalides hospital and veterans” home. Paintings from this movement, like In the Wheat, were painted (20 pts)",
        "en plein air and are collected by the Mus´ee d’Orsay. Berthe Morisot exhibited her work in 1874 alongside a painting of Le Havre, in which (10 pts)",
        "hazy ship masts stand quietly in a foggy early morning, that gave this movement its name. For ten points, name this French art movement named for a painting of a Sunrise created by Claude Monet."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Impressionism",
        "word forms like Impressionist movement",
        "Impression, Sunrise",
        "Impression, soleil levant"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One man with this surname was the longest-serving governor of New York and served as Vice President under both Thomas Jefferson and James Madison. Another man with this surname sponsored the construction of the (20 pts)",
        "Erie Canal, which was nicknamed his “ditch.” In addition to George and DeWitt, another man with this surname signed (10 pts)",
        "NAFTA into law and served as the governor of Arkansas; that man came under fire for his affair with the White House intern Monica Lewinsky. For ten points, give this surname shared by politicians Bill and Hillary."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Clinton",
        "George Clinton, DeWitt Clinton, Bill Clinton, William Jefferson Clinton III, and/or Hillary Clinton"
      ]
    }
  ]
}